Preliminary Guide to the J. Walter Thompson Company. Frankfurt Office. Audiovisual Materials, 1956-1993 and undated RL.00692
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
J. Walter Thompson Company. Frankfurt Office. Audiovisual Materials
1956-1993 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
J. Walter Thompson Company. Frankfurt Office
RL.00692
220 Linear Feet
Founded in 1864, the J. Walter Thompson Company (JWT) is one of the oldest and largest enduring advertising agencies in the United States. The Frankfurt Office opened in 1952. The J. Walter Thompson Company Frankfurt Office Audiovisual Materials span the years 1956-1993 and consist of 16mm and 35mm films, videocassettes and slides that document print advertisements and television commercials produced by the Frankfurt Office for the German and continental European markets. Companies represented include Braun, De Beers, Elida Gibbs (Chesebrough-Pond's), Findus, Ford, Glückslee, Hoffman's, Jacobs (Kraft), Kellogg's, Kraft, Maggi, Pepsi, Sunlicht (Unilever), and Wick. Acquired as part of the John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History.
5178 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is restricted.
Original audiovisual materials are closed to patron use. Some use copies are available in the collection. Otherwise, Research Services staff need to produce use copies before contents can be accessed.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The J. Walter Thompson Company. Frankfurt Office. Audiovisual Materials were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1996.
Collection Overview
The J. Walter Thompson Company (JWT) Frankfurt Office Audiovisual Materials span the years 1956-1993 and consist of 16mm and 35mm films, videocassettes and slides that document print advertisements and television commercials produced by the Frankfurt Office for the German and continental European markets. Companies represented include Braun, De Beers, Elida Gibbs (Chesebrough-Pond's), Findus, Ford, Glückslee, Hoffman's, Jacobs (Kraft), Kellogg's, Kraft, Maggi, Pepsi, Sunlicht (Unilever), and Wick.
Collection Arrangement
Collection is arranged in five series: Commercials by Client; Oversize Materials; Videocassettes; Slides; and Use Copies.
Related Material
Related materials may be found in the following collections of the Hartman Center:
J. Walter Thompson Company Frankfurt Office Advertisements
J. Walter Thompson Company International Advertisements
J. Walter Thompson Company International Offices Records.
McCann-Erickson Audiovisual Collection
Slides (photographs); 16mm; Television commercials -- Europe; Television commercials -- Germany; Advertising agencies -- Germany; Advertising agencies -- Europe; Advertising -- Germany -- History; Advertising -- Germany; Television advertising -- Germany; Television advertising -- Europe; Advertising campaigns -- Germany; Advertising campaigns -- Europe; Advertising -- Europe; 35mm; Videocassettes; Ford Motor Company; De Beers Consolidated Mines; Findus (Firm); John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History; Kellogg Company; J. Walter Thompson Company. Frankfurt Office; J. Walter Thompson Company; Pepsi-Cola Company; Unilever (Firm); Kraft Foods Company; Maggi AG; Chesebrough-Pond's.; Braun
- Commercials by Client, 1956-1992 and undated
  Scope and Contents note
  [Primarily 35mm and 16mm films with some early forms of video tape scattered throughout.]
  - 3M (17 reels), 1961-1965 (Box 1)
  - Aluminum Secretariat, Ltd. (1 reel), 1960s (Box 1)
  - After Eight: see Oversize Reels (Box 1)
  - Adams/Pfeilring (16 reels), 1977-1980 (Box 2)
  - Apargatas (1 reel), 1980s (Box 2)
  - Aqua Velva (3 reels), 1960s (Box 2)
  - Baldur (2 reels), 1983 (Box 3)
  - Bausparkasse (1 reel), 1972 (Box 3)
  - Bennetton (2 reels), 1987 (Box 3)
  - Bissel (14 reels), 1961-1966 (Box 3)
  - Bayer (19 reels), 1959-1961 (Box 4)
  - Braun (21 reels), 1971-1973 (Box 5)
  - Braun (20 reels), 1973-1974 (Box 6)
  - Braun (20 reels), 1975-1976 (Box 7)
  - Braun (17 reels), 1977-1978 (Box 8)
  - Brinkmann (24 reels), 1958-1961 (Box 9)
  - Brinkmann (24 reels), 1961-1964 (Box 10)
    [Some items reformatted: See Use Copies series.]
  - Brinkmann (11 reels), undated (Box 11)
  - Buer (20 reels), 1973-1977 (Box 12)
  - Burger King (18 reels), 1976-1985 (Box 13)
  - Bristol-Myers (3 reels), 1963-1964 (Box 14)
  - Bundesbahn (1 reel), 1970s (Box 14)
  - Caltex-Boron (2 reels), 1960s (Box 14)
  - Campari (5 reels), 1981-1985 (Box 14)
  - Chesterfield (1 reel), 1971 (Box 14)
  - Charles Hosie (Bacardi): See also Oversize Reels (18 reels), 1972-1988 (Box 15)
  - Charles Hosie (Bacardi): See also Oversize Reels (6 reels), 1985-1988 (Box 16)
  - Coop supermarket (1 reel), 1984 (Box 16)
  - Commodore (1 reel), 1980s (Box 16)
  - Dralon (1 reel), 1970s (Box 16)
  - Chevron: See also Oversize Reels (19 reels), 1965-1970 (Box 17)
  - DeBeers: See also Oversize Reels (7 reels), 1960s (Box 18, Digital-materials RL00692-SET-0001)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Digital preservation and use copies have been created for some of the film reels in this box. Contact Research Services for further information.
  - DeBeers: See also Oversize Reels (6 reels), 1960s-1970s (Box 19, Digital-materials RL00692-SET-0001)
  - DeBeers: See also Oversize Reels (18 reels), 1977-1989 and undated (Box 20, Digital-materials RL00692-SET-0001)
  - Dortmunder (6 reels), 1970-1977 (Box 21)
  - DuBonnett (1 reel), 1960 (Box 21)
  - Dt. Bundesbank (3 reels), 1966 (Box 21)
  - Dt. Wein (4 reels), 1969, 1978-1980 (Box 21)
  - Dt. Wein (19 reels), 1970-1978 (Box 22)
  - Dub Schultheis: See also Oversize Reels (21 reels), 1971-1977 (Box 23)
  - Elida (12 reels), 1960s, 1980-1981 (Box 24)
  - Elida (22 reels), 1960-1963 (Box 25)
  - Elida (23 reels), 1963-1966 (Box 26)
  - Elida (21 reels), 1967-1969 (Box 27)
  - Elida (21 reels), 1969-1973 (Box 28)
  - Elida (21 reels), 1973-1976 (Box 29)
  - Elida (18 reels), 1976-1979 (Box 30)
  - Elida (18 reels), 1979-1980 (Box 31)
  - Findus (17 reels), 1962-1966 (Box 32)
  - Findus (17 reels), 1963-1970 (Box 33)
  - Ford (24 reels), 1959-1972, 1982-1984 (Box 34)
  - Ford (22 reels), 1959-1962 (Box 35)
  - Ford (10 reels), 1960s, 1982 (Box 36)
  - Ford (22 reels), 1962-1966 (Box 37)
  - Ford (19 reels), 1966-1972 (Box 38)
  - Ford (19 reels), 1972-1983 (Box 39)
  - FAZ (10 reels), 1982-1986 (Box 40)
  - Florida (4 reels), 1959-1960s (Box 40)
  - Groome (1 reel), 1960s (Box 40)
  - Glücksklee (17 reels), 1969-1971 (Box 41)
  - Glücksklee (17 reels), 1972-1976 (Box 42)
  - Glücksklee (17 reels), 1977-1980 (Box 43)
  - Hoffman's (22 reels), 1962-1966 (Box 44)
  - Hoffman's (22 reels), 1967-1969 (Box 45)
  - Hoffman's (20 reels), 1969-1978 (Box 46)
  - IZE Strom (5 reels), 1980-1981 (Box 47)
  - JWT USA (2 reels), 1960s (Box 47)
  - Khasana (7 reels), 1960-1961 (Box 47)
  - Kodak (2 reels), 1959 (Box 47)
  - Jacobs: See also Oversize Reels (22 reels), 1965-1969 (Box 48)
  - Jacobs: See also Oversize Reels (22 reels), 1969-1974 (Box 49)
  - Jacobs: See also Oversize Reels (22 reels), 1974-1976 (Box 50)
  - Jacobs: See also Oversize Reels (19 reels), 1976-1977 (Box 51)
  - Jacobs: See also Oversize Reels (18 reels), 1977-1978 (Box 52)
  - Jacobs: See also Oversize Reels (18 reels), 1978-1979 (Box 53)
  - Jacobs: See also Oversize Reels (18 reels), 1979-1980 (Box 54)
  - Jacobs: See also Oversize Reels (15 reels), 1981-1983 (Box 55)
  - Jacobs: See also Oversize Reels (9 reels), 1987-1988 (Box 56)
  - Johnson (22 reels), 1964-1965 (Box 57)
  - Johnson (22 reels), 1966-1970 (Box 58)
  - Johnson (13 reels), 1969-1971, 1981-1983 (Box 59)
  - Johnson (11 reels), 1972-1983 (Box 60)
  - Jora (19 reels), 1963-1967 (Box 61)
  - Kellogg's: See also Oversize Reels (22 reels), 1959-1963 (Box 62)
  - Kellogg's: See also Oversize Reels (14 reels), 1960-1985 (Box 63)
  - Kellogg's: See also Oversize Reels (22 reels), 1963-1970 (Box 64)
  - Kellogg's: See also Oversize Reels (22 reels), 1973-1975 (Box 65)
  - Kellogg's: See also Oversize Reels (19 reels), 1976-1979 (Box 66)
  - Kellogg's: See also Oversize Reels (15 reels), 1979-1986 (Box 67)
  - Kellogg's: See also Oversize Reels (17 reels), 1979-1987 (Box 68)
  - Kellogg's: See also Oversize Reels (20 reels), 1980-1989 (Box 69)
  - Kellogg's: See also Oversize Reels (15 reels), 1960s-1991 (Box 70)
  - Kraft: See also Oversize Reels (15 reels), 1957-1990 (Box 71)
  - Kraft: See also Oversize Reels (22 reels), 1959-1960 (Box 72)
  - Kraft: See also Oversize Reels (15 reels), 1960-1990 (Box 73a)
  - Kraft: See also Oversize Reels (22 reels), 1960-1961 (Box 73b)
  - Kraft: See also Oversize Reels (22 reels), 1961 (Box 74)
  - Kraft: See also Oversize Reels (22 reels), 1961-1962 (Box 75)
  - Kraft: See also Oversize Reels (22 reels), 1962-1964 (Box 76)
  - Kraft: See also Oversize Reels (22 reels), 1964-1966 (Box 77)
  - Kraft: See also Oversize Reels (22 reels), 1966-1967 (Box 78)
  - Kraft: See also Oversize Reels (22 reels), 1967-1968 (Box 79)
  - Kraft: See also Oversize Reels (22 reels), 1968-1969 (Box 80)
  - Kraft: See also Oversize Reels (22 reels), 1969-1970 (Box 81)
  - Kraft: See also Oversize Reels (22 reels), 1970-1971 (Box 82)
  - Kraft: See also Oversize Reels (22 reels), 1971-1974 (Box 83)
  - Kraft: See also Oversize Reels (22 reels), 1973-1975 (Box 84)
  - Kraft: See also Oversize Reels (22 reels), 1976-1977 (Box 85)
  - Kraft: See also Oversize Reels (18 reels), 1977-1979 (Box 86)
  - Kraft: See also Oversize Reels (27 reels), 1979-1983 and undated (Box 87)
  - Kraft: See also Oversize Reels (20 reels), 1986-1991 (Box 88)
  - Maggi (19 reels), 1956-1959 (Box 89a)
  - Maggi (19 reels), 1959-1960 (Box 89b)
  - Maggi (19 reels), 1960-1961 (Box 90)
  - Maggi (21 reels), 1961-1964 (Box 91)
  - Maggi (20 reels), 1964-1966 (Box 92)
  - Maggi (17 reels), 1967-1969 (Box 93)
  - Maggi (13 reels), 1971-1972 (Box 94)
  - Maggi (11 reels), 1960s (Box 95)
  - Mattel (3 reels), 1987 (Box 96)
  - Mentadent (3 reels), 1987 (Box 96)
  - Milupa-Pauly GmbH (5 reels), 1965 (Box 96)
  - MiniMAL (9 reels), 1990-1991 (Box 97)
  - Murine (5 reels), 1960s (Box 97)
  - Nestlé (1 reel), 1960s (Box 97)
  - Pan Am (3 reels), 1960s or 1970s (Box 97)
  - Pan Am (22 reels), 1968-1975 (Box 98)
  - Pepsi: See also Oversize Reels (6 reels), 1960s (Box 99)
  - Pepsi: See also Oversize Reels (24 reels), 1961-1964 (Box 100)
  - Pepsi: See also Oversize Reels (24 reels), 1964-1969 (Box 101)
  - Pepsi: See also Oversize Reels (20 reels), 1970-1977 (Box 102)
  - Pepsi: See also Oversize Reels (18 reels), 1977-1978 (Box 103)
  - Pepsi: See also Oversize Reels (18 reels), 1979-1987 (Box 104)
  - Ponds (18 reels), 1959-1967 (Box 105)
  - Pott (6 reels), 1959 (Box 106)
  - Reese (5 reels), 1961 (Box 106)
  - Rowntree: See also Oversize Reels (7 reels), 1965-1982 (Box 106)
  - Rolex: See also Oversize Reels (11 reels), 1960s-1970s (Box 107)
  - SAGA (4 reels), 1967-1968 (Box 108)
  - Suchard (1 reel), 1987 (Box 108)
  - Suwa (2 reels), 1960 (Box 108)
  - Swakara (4 reels), 1974-1975 (Box 108)
  - Schwartzkopf (18 reels), 1960-1963 (Box 109)
  - Seagram (14 reels), 1980-1987 (Box 110)
  - Sohnlein (20 reels), 1958-1964 (Box 111)
  - Singer (22 reels), 1966-1974 (Box 112)
  - Singer (1 reel), 1960s (Box 113)
  - Sudmilch (9 reels), 1976-1977 (Box 113)
  - Sprengez (11 reels), 1963-1966 (Box 113)
  - Sprengez (21 reels), 1959-1963 (Box 114)
  - Sunlicht (11 reels), 1957-1960 (Box 115a)
  - Sunlicht (11 reels), 1960s-1984 (Box 115b)
  - Sunlicht (19 reels), 1960 (Box 116)
  - Sunlicht (21 reels), 1960 (Box 117)
  - Sunlicht (19 reels), 1961 (Box 118)
  - Sunlicht (21 reels), 1961-1963 (Box 119)
  - Sunlicht (22 reels), 1963-1964 (Box 120)
  - Sunlicht (22 reels), 1964-1965 (Box 121)
  - Sunlicht (21 reels), 1965 (Box 122)
  - Sunlicht (21 reels), 1965-1966 (Box 123)
  - Sunlicht (21 reels), 1966 (Box 124)
  - Sunlicht (21 reels), 1966-1967 (Box 125a)
  - Sunlicht (21 reels), 1967 (Box 125b)
  - Sunlicht (19 reels), 1968 (Box 126)
  - Sunlicht (21 reels), 1968-1969 (Box 127)
  - Sunlicht (19 reels), 1969-1970 (Box 128)
  - Sunlicht (21 reels), 1971-1972 (Box 129)
  - Sunlicht (20 reels), 1973-1976 (Box 130)
  - Sunlicht (17 reels), 1976-1979 (Box 131)
  - Sunlicht (20 reels), 1981-1983 and undated (Box 132)
  - Triumph (20 reels), 1962-1965 (Box 133)
  - Triumph (4 reels), 1960s (Box 134)
  - V fz (?): See also Oversize Reels (3 reels), 1960s (Box 134)
  - Waschmittel (1 reel), 1960s (Box 134)
  - Wrigley's (1 reel), 1960s (Box 134)
  - Vereinigte Papierwarenfabriken/Camflia (20 reels), 1968-1981 (Box 135)
  - Vileda (8 reels), 1963-1964 (Box 136)
  - Wolf (13 reels), 1965-1966 (Box 136)
  - Wick (21 reels), 1957-1960 (Box 137)
  - Wick (13 reels), 1960s-1986 (Box 138)
  - Wick (23 reels), 1961-1963 (Box 139)
  - Wick (20 reels), 1964-1968 (Box 140)
  - Wick (21 reels), 1968-1975 (Box 141)
  - Wick (19 reels), 1975-1977 (Box 142)
  - Wick (19 reels), 1977-1979 (Box 143)
  - Wick (18 reels), 1979-1980 (Box 144)
  - Wick (17 reels), 1980-1984 (Box 145)
  - Compilation reels (Musterolles): See also Oversize Reels (8 reels), 1960s-1970s (Box 146)
    [Multiple clients and numerous commercials on each reel presumably used for corporate or new business presentations.]
  - Compilation reels (Musterolles): See also Oversize Reels (15 reels), 1960s-1970s (Box 147)
  - Corporate presentations: See also Oversize Reels (10 reels), 1960s-1970s (Box 148)
    [Mainly 16mm and video reels]
  - Unidentified (10 reels), 1960s-1970 (Box 149)
  - Unidentified (12 reels), 1960s-1970s (Box 150)
  - Unidentified (9 reels), 1960s-1980s (Box 151)
- Oversize Reels, 1968-1991 and undated
  - After Eight, 1980-1981 (Box 152)
  - After Eight, 1980-1981 (Box 153)
  - After Eight, 1980 (Box 154)
  - Charles Hosie (Bacardi), undated (Box 155)
  - Charles Hosie (Bacardi), undated (Box 156)
  - Chevron, undated (Box 157)
  - DeBeers, undated (Box 158)
  - DeBeers, 1980 (Box 159)
  - DeBeers, 1982-1983 (Box 160)
  - Jacobs, 1968 (Box 161)
  - Kraft (Miracoli), 1990 (Box 162)
  - Kraft (Miracoli), undated (Box 163)
  - Kraft, undated (Box 164)
  - Pepsi, undated (Box 165)
  - Dub Schultheis, undated (Box 166)
  - Kellogg's, 1973 (Box 167)
  - Rountree, 1991 (Box 168)
  - Rolex (Traveling Through Time), undated (Box 169)
  - Rolex, undated (Box 170)
  - Rolex (A Strange Planet), undated (Box 171)
  - Suchard, 1987 (Box 172)
  - V fz, undated (Box 173)
  - Compilation reels (Musterolles), undated (Box 174)
  - Corporate presentations, undated (Box 175)
  - Unidentified, undated (Box 176a)
  - Unidentified (Berlin Wall), undated (Box 176b)
- Video, 1980s-1993 and undated
  [Mainly Umatic and PAL format]
  - Commercials by client including Dt. Bank, Mentdadent, ATM/Mr. Cash, Jacobs TV history, De Beers, Andrex, Kraft, DEA, Elida, Bacardi. (Box 177)
  - Commercials by clients and competitors including Lowenbrau, Perrier, MRM's TV history, Young & Rubicam's Amaretto (1988), Bacardi TV history, CD case history, Tires for the World, Nestle's chocolate eggs, various Easter Egg commercials, 1980s (Box 178)
  - Compilations of commercials including fruit drinks, Russian compilation, and several JWT highlights (1988, 1992, undated). Also contains 1 audio cassette of radio spots for various products, circa 1992 (Box 179)
  - Mostly showreels (presumably compilations of commercials used for various presentations) including Effective Creativity Showreel (1992), JWT Europe Multinational clients (1993), EuroMontage (1989), circa 1993 (Box 180)
  - Corporate presentations including Satellite Wars (1989), JWT-London An Approach to New Business, Windows of Change: Key social Trends in Developing Nations (1988), A Country Called Deutschland (1991), Eyes on Thompson (1991-1992), JWT--A Worldwide Powerhouse, The Brain Game, circa 1990 (Box 181)
- Slides, 1980s and undated
  [Images of print advertisements used in various corporate or new business presentations. While most are arranged by client, others appear to be a mix of clients (JWT and competitive). There may also be slides of statistics, charts, etc. which were used in presentations as well.]
  - Includes Braun, Dt. Wein, and Alpi, undated (Box 182)
  - Includes De Beers, Platin, Glucksklee, Wick, and Johnson. (Box 183)
  - Includes case history or credential presentations for Bacardi, CD, Platin, Ford, Phillips, and De Beers. (Box 184)
  - Includes Ford, undated (Box 185)
  - Includes Ford, Kraft, Hercules, undated (Box 186)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 187)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 188)
  - Corporate presentations related to JWT history, Phillips, plus some miscellaneous, undated (Box 189)
  - Corporate presentations including BOR presentation, Okal case history, and various miscellaneous and unidentified, undated (Box 190)
  - Includes case histories for Mr. Cash, pet food, Andrex, and Wick; UK print ads, the New German; Joe O'Donnell visit in 1986 History and Today's Management. Also contains the audio cassette tape Deutschlands Jingle-Hits (3 sets) and an audio record for Friskies (6 copies), circa 1986 (Box 191)
- Use Copies, 1 box
  [Reformatted commercials open for researchers.]
  - DVD 1 (Box 192)
    [From box 11: Brinkman 13 F15-8-Co2 Nach Hause Kommender Munn; Marlboro TV spot 1315-O-M-98 Feitung 20"; Brinkman M8 Mischury der TV spots 1-6. From box 105: Kruse Film No. 638 Pond's Q-Tips 1-2; Q-Tips 3115-5-Q-40; Q-Tips 3115-9-Q-41. From box 10: Brinkman No. 193 Marlboro 1-2, No. 194 Marlboro 1-2, No. 8 Marlboro 1-2, No. 396 Gloria 1-2. From box 33: Findus Schlemmer flet II 1-2, Findus No. 761 1-2. From box 32: Findus No. 343, No. 517 1-3, No. 228 1-3.]